<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of the Church of England by law established necessary to be considered in order to a more firm and full settlement of peace both at home and abroad : in a letter to a bishop of the present constitution / by an English Catholick.</title>
            <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61423</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5423</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38300</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17288871</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17288871</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106332</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61423)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106332)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1103:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of the Church of England by law established necessary to be considered in order to a more firm and full settlement of peace both at home and abroad : in a letter to a bishop of the present constitution / by an English Catholick.</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints to John Stephens, who also wrote under the pseudonym of Socrates Christianus.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Establishment and disestablishment.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Government.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Church of England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:106332:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106332:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The CASE of the <hi>Church of England</hi> By Law Eſtabliſhed, Neceſſary to be conſidered, in Order to a more firm and full Settlement of Peace both at Home and Abroad.</head>
            <head type="sub">In a Letter to a Biſhop of the preſent Conſtitution, by an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Catholick.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHEN you deſired to diſcourſe with me, I was very glad of it; for I know none of your Order I ſhould more gladly have diſcourſed with than your ſelf: But my Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations were greatly diſappointed, when after I had walked more than five Miles for that purpoſe, you firſt permitted much of my time to be loſt by ordinary Diſcourſe, not ſo much as of any Buſineſs; and, at laſt, as ſoon as I moved any thing towards it, took ſuch occaſion to prevent any farther Proceedings in <hi>Conference,</hi> either then, or at any time elſe, as looked as if you in truth declined what you before ſeemed to deſire. I expected to have received from you the Subject of our Diſcourſe; but ſince you was not pleaſed to vouchſafe me that Favour, I ſhall to you, and (for rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which will appear hereafter) to all, give a plain Account of what I think may reaſonably be expected from me.</p>
            <p>I have from <hi>my Youth</hi> been diſpoſed to <hi>Retirement,</hi> and yet for all that always ſo heartily affected to <hi>the Service of God and my Country,</hi> that upon any juſt Occaſion I have been as ready to <hi>appear in Publick</hi> as any, and without any reſpect to any <hi>private Interest.</hi> This is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by what I have Printed ſince the Revolution, (not to mention
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106332:2"/>other Matters:) And ſoon after I had received my <hi>Quietus</hi> from that Service, (as I apprehended it) I was, by a <hi>Secret Conduct of Providence,</hi> engaged in another, which had been much in my Heart for many Years, for the more immediate Service of our Great So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign; and, by ſeveral Steps unforeſeen by any Mortal, neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to enter into the <hi>most Sacred Imployment,</hi> unleſs I would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert that Service, and let it fall; and to proceed from a private Room to a publick Church, and from one to another, till I and my little Company were brought into the very <hi>Heart of the City:</hi> and then I began to be more ſenſible of the Divine Hand in it, and what our Buſineſs was; <hi>viz.</hi> to bear a Publick, but tacit <hi>Teſtimony</hi> againſt the Corruptions and Neglect of <hi>the most Solemn part of the Chriſtian Worſhip.</hi> And that I continued for above <hi>Two Years</hi> daily with a <hi>Liturgy reſtored</hi> in the principal Matters to the Primitive Integrity, which I printed, and preſented to the Arch Biſhop, and Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> and others, and let it be publiſhed; and in the Preface gave ſufficient <hi>Admonition</hi> of thoſe Faults I have mentioned. But when I found it ſo neglected by thoſe, who were moſt obliged to take Notice of it, I began to fear it might be but the Expoſing of ſo Sacred a thing to Contempt, if we continued in that publick man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; yet did not think fit to deſert that Poſt till I had either a Prohibition to proceed, or an <hi>Invitation</hi> to depart to ſome other Station; and ſuch I ſoon had, a very extraordinary one, to a very <hi>convenient Retirement.</hi> After I came thither, <hi>the Scandals</hi> I had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore received from the Unfaithfulneſs, Tepedity, and Unconcerned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſuch, as of all men I thought moſt obliged to take Care of the Service of God, and the Peace and Welfare of the Nation, were ſo often by Letters I received from <hi>London</hi> recalled to my Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, that at laſt I reſolved upon a farther and more exact <hi>Review of what is called the Reformation,</hi> which ſeems to have been the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Buſineſs of that Retirement. When I had ſatisfied my ſelf in that matter, I gave a plain Account of the things of moſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, both to the State, and to the Church, which I had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, to Two of His Majeſty's Privy-Council, and reſolved for my ſelf to do what I could to extricate my ſelf out of all that Guilt and Wickedneſs I found this Nation involved in, and to make my own Cauſe good, whatever others would do. And for that purpoſe I could not think of any Expedient more proper, than to draw up a plain <hi>Profeſſion of my Faith,</hi> and to make an Offer thereof, and of <hi>Communion</hi> to the next Catholick Church, which I take to be that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106332:2"/>of <hi>France;</hi> and a little kind of Overture I then made of it to a private Friend in <hi>London.</hi> When I had done this, we ſoon had <hi>Occaſion</hi> to think of removing thence, and upon our Removal, Opportunity to make ſome ſtay at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and to peruſe what Books and Manuſcripts I thought fit there; and when I had done that, a fair <hi>Invitation</hi> to come nearer <hi>London.</hi> And then I thought fit to write to the Biſhop of the Dioceſs whence I came, and where I was concerned, to the Biſhop of the Dioceſs to which I came, and to the Arch-Biſhop of the Province, concerning theſe matters, who were all I thought my ſelf obliged to for any account of what I did; but I deſired an Opportunity to repreſent them to a Synod: For I could not ſatisfie my ſelf to ſecure my own Intereſt, unleſs I did what I could for the Service of my Countrey alſo, eſpecially ſince we have a Peace ſo happily concluded by ſo many States, without any great Danger of any thing than what is like to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived by Diſſentions in the Church, and the ſecret Guilt of Sacrilege and Schiſm, both in this and other Nations. And therefore when I found no hopes of any Opportunity of repreſenting theſe matters before the Church Collective in a Synod, there was no other way for me of doing it at all but before the Church Diffuſive by the Preſs. And for divers Reaſons I thought nothing more proper to begin with than a Diſcourſe of <hi>Prayers for the Dead,</hi> with a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face concerning the Neceſſity and Advantage of a Review of theſe matters by the State, ſince the preſent Governours of the Church would not trouble themſelves about them. And this, my Lord, I hope, will fully anſwer part of your miſtake concerning me. I ſhall next tell you plainly, What were the <hi>Scandals</hi> which princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally moved me to this Review, ſo far as is ſufficient for my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; and then, What were the principal <hi>Matters</hi> which I <hi>obſerved</hi> in it, and think moſt neceſſary for a farther Conſideration at preſent.</p>
            <p>Of thoſe <hi>Scandals,</hi> there is one of which I have long ſince, and often complained, both in private and publick, but with ſo little Succeſs, as doth not a little aggravate the Sin and Scandal to me: It is, that, having ſo great Encouragement for Learning, ſuch Numbers of Learned Men, ſuch Abundance of Shipping, and all Neceſſaries, ſuch Commerce, Footing, and Plantations in ſo many Foreign Parts among Infidels, there hath been no Care taken by the Governours of this Reformed Church for the <hi>Propagation of Religion</hi> among the Infidels, or the Promotion of ſincere Piety in our own Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106332:3"/>but, inſtead of ſending Miſſioners of the Goſpel, ſuffering them to be filled with the Miniſters of Satan, the moſt ſcandalous People of the Nation; and for Relief of the poor <hi>Negroes,</hi> whom their worſe than Infidel Maſters will not ſuffer to be inſtructed in Chriſtianity, and to be baptized, leaſt they ſhould loſe their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, not ſo much as a Bill brought in, or one Motion made in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, where they ſit, and are many times as buſie, as Solicitors, in private Caſes of temporal Concern.</p>
            <p>This is not a little aggravated by the cold Entertainment which Doctor <hi>Bray</hi>'s good <hi>Propoſal</hi> had in this Nation, not only among the Gentry and People in the Country, but among the Citizens and Traders, and even thoſe very Peſons who approved and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended it to the Charitable Contributions of others; and after it had been thus ſent on begging for ſo inconſiderable a Sum as <hi>Three Thouſand Pounds,</hi> which was as much as it required, has been held in Suſpence for ſome Years before it could be raiſed, if it be raiſed yet. And this, if I miſtake not, is the greateſt matter that ever was attempted by any of this Church. What Multitudes of Souls muſt have died in Ignorance and Infidelity, and in ſcandalous Sins, through the Unfaithfulneſs and Neglect of this Glorious Reformed Church? Can any Man in great Place in this Church think of this without Horror and Amazement for the Account they muſt one day give for it, if they have any thing of true and ſincere Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity in them? Could ſuch a Man reproach another for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending <hi>Xavier,</hi> or ſo much as think of that glorious Saint, his admirable Virtues and Works, confeſſed and commended even by Proteſtants themſelves, and not be confounded at the Thought of it? Are not he, and many others of the <hi>Popes Miſſioners,</hi> the Shame and Reproach of ſuch Perſons, and of ſuch a Reformation, in this World, and like to riſe up in Judgment againſt them in the next? And who can believe that ſuch a Reformation as this was of God, or is indowed with an Apoſtolical Spirit?</p>
            <p>I need not mention <hi>Particulars</hi> of the like Unfaithfulneſs and Neglect at home: If <hi>publick Records</hi> be examined, and the Good promoted, or but propoſed in Parliament by this Order be compared with what they have hindered or oppoſed, I doubt it will be found upon Record that this Reformed Order have been very inſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant Inſtruments for the Good of the Nation, if not much more inſtrumental to hinder it. But we need not be at ſo much trouble as that of Searching Records; if <hi>the viſible State of the Nation</hi> be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106332:3"/>conſidered, it is manifeſt and undeniable of what Communion <hi>the most Scandalous part of the Nation</hi> are, and under whoſe Diſcipline, if that may be called Diſcipline, which was once wiſhed, 140 years ſince, but never practiſed to this day. Another great part of the Nation, who have <hi>little more of Religion than a bare Profeſſion, and going to Church on Sundays,</hi> ſuch as the greateſt part of moſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Pariſhes in <hi>England</hi> are, are of the ſame Communion, and under the Care and Inſtruction of the ſame Perſons. And if we enquire into the Occaſions of ſo great Increaſe of <hi>Atheiſm, Deiſm, and Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity,</hi> I have not in 30 years laſt paſt diſcovered any more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and effectual, than the Scandal of the Unconcernedneſs of the Clergy for the Promotion of the Religion they profeſs, and their eager purſuit of their own Promotion and Preferment in the Church. Nor do I think there is any more common and effectual Occaſion of ſo great numbers of <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> than that Coldneſs, Formality, and Emptineſs of a true Spiritual Life and Power which they obſerved in the Generality of the Clergy, of all Ranks and Degrees; and thereupon wander to ſeek for it where they can find it. For there is a certain <hi>Spiritual Senſation,</hi> as a learned Man of your own calls it, by which devout experienced Souls can perceive ſuch a ſecret Power and Life in ſome Perſons and Books, as that of the Imitation of Chriſt, which have but a mean, ſimple, outward Appearance, as they perceive to be really wanting in others ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently furniſhed with Learning and Humane Reaſon to recommend them to thoſe, whoſe Religion is more ſuperficial or notional. And ſuch I believe are many among the Diſſenters, who would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have ſought for what they wanted abroad, if they could have found it at home.</p>
            <p>Beſides all this, there is another very notorious, which I ſhall not mention here, having a more ſpecial Occaſion to take notice of it preſently: and I ſhall but mention what was not a little Scandalous to me, becauſe not ſo notorious to others; the obſtinate and wilful Neglect of theſe two great Parts of our Religion, the <hi>Peculiar So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of the Worſhip,</hi> (of which I have ſaid enough in the <hi>Preface to the Liturgy</hi>) and of <hi>the Diſcipline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things, I preſume, will not be denied to be ſufficient Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to a conſiderate Man to examine the Root of a Religion, which brings forth ſuch Fruits: and now I ſhall tell you (not all that I obſerved in my Review; that would be too much for what I now deſign, but) ſo much as is neceſſary and ſufficient for the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106332:4"/>Concluſions I make upon it. <hi>Three</hi> things, I believe, will go near to determine all Queſtions needful concerning the Reformation: What were the Cauſes, for which? What the Authority, by which, it was done? And what the Fruits and Effects? Of the moving Cauſes enough is ſaid for the preſent in the late <hi>Letter and Anſwer to the Young-Man, p.</hi> 2, 3. And much of the Fruits I have here noted already; but there is one ſo natural to the Root, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, and of ſo ſpreading and peſtiferous a nature, that I thought fit to reſerve the mentioning of it for this place.</p>
            <p>The very <hi>Root</hi> of the preſent Reformation, which was at laſt Eſtabliſhed by Act of Parliament, 1 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 1. was <hi>Cranmer,</hi> from whom the Conſecrators of <hi>Matt. Parker,</hi> the Principal of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Succeſſion of Legal Biſhops in this Nation, received their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; ſo that he is the <hi>Common Anceſtor</hi> of all. What his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples were, and to what Exceſſes his Flattery of the Civil Magiſtrate proceeded, may be ſeen in the late <hi>Abſtract of the Vindication of the Rights of the Church, c.</hi> 8. even to the betraying of thoſe Sacred and Divine Rights, and cenſuring even the Apoſtles themſelves: And it is no wonder if from ſuch an Anceſtor, and ſuch Principles, have proceeded a Progeny of Flatterers of Princes for their own temporal Intereſt, to the Diſturbance of all mutual Confidence between them and the People, and Deſtruction of whole Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies. For this, tho' notorious before, we need look no farther than the laſt of the ſecond Race of Kings ſince the Reformation, plainly betrayed into thoſe illegal Actions (juſtifiable indeed by thoſe Principles, but not by the Fundamental Laws of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government) which are the
<note n="*" place="margin">In the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were the Rights of the People inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; in the Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſions the Rights of the Church alſo. It was touching the <hi>Accurſed</hi> thing.</note> principal things evident againſt him, by thoſe falſe Principles, and the deceitful Flattery of ſuch as preached up and pretended as much to Loyalty, Non-reſiſtance, and paſſive Obedience, as any; but ſoon diſcovered what was in the bottom of thoſe Pretences when there was occaſion. But admirable is <hi>the Providence of God,</hi> who hath not only given us at laſt occaſion to ſee the <hi>Decitfulneſs and Treacherouſneſs of thoſe Principles;</hi> and brought things to that State, that neither can King <hi>James</hi> excuſe his Actions, but by thoſe Principles, which yet he hath ſpecial rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to abhor; nor King <hi>William</hi> and the Nation juſtifie theirs, but by
<note n="†" place="margin">Both the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation</hi> and the <hi>Oath of Supremacy</hi> ſeem Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, Sacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical, and Perjury, to cauſe Flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, ſubvert the Laws, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie <hi>K. James,</hi> and be a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: and not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, but aggravated by Qu. <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi>'s In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction.</note> diſowning and diſclaiming thoſe, and aſſerting and adhering to thoſe of the true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government; but beſides, by a new Diviſion and Contention in the Church, hath extorted a juſt Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Truth, (with a plain Conviction of the contrary He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106332:4"/>which few or none before would ſo much as own or confeſs. The <hi>Eraſtian Hereſie</hi> you know I mean; and the Conviction may be ſeen in the <hi>Abſtract.</hi> But no Conviction, tho' never ſo clear, will ever free this Nation from a continual Succeſſion of ſuch a peſtiferous Brood, till the State it ſelf caſt out the accurſed thing, which that Sacrilegious, Treacherous <hi>Achan</hi> brought into it. And ſuch it is indeed; for if his Principles be <hi>Hereſie,</hi> the Practice in the State is certainly <hi>Sacrilege,</hi> and <hi>Sacrilege</hi> of no ordinary Nature or degree. And how curſed a thing that is may be ſeen in Sir <hi>Henry Spelman</hi>'s two Treatiſes, one but lately printed. Such curſed Fruit proceeding from this Root, all may ſee, and many have felt, and more may, if they take not warning.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Authority</hi> by which this Reformation was Eſtabliſhed, as aforeſaid, was meerly and intirely Lay: the Biſhops in the Houſe made Speeches againſt it; the Convocation of the Clergy ſent up a Remonſtrance againſt it; and the Univerſities declared againſt it. This Authority therefore was incompetent; and that <hi>Authority,</hi> which by it was <hi>introduced into the Church,</hi> when the other Biſhops were turned out, <hi>Schiſmatical,</hi> and null; and beſides, meerly <hi>Political,</hi> even in its Original, (as is briefly noted in the <hi>Letter to the Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi>) and nothing truly Apoſtolical in it: for that <hi>Cranmer</hi> had implicitly renounced and diſowned, and wickedly, heretically, and treacherouſly introduced one meerly Political into the Church in the place of it, by his
<note n="*" place="margin">This the <hi>Hiſtory of the Reformation</hi> falſly charges upon <hi>Bonner,</hi> who was not ſo much as Biſhop then.</note> 
               <hi>ſtrange Project of Commiſſions;</hi> and the
<note n="†" place="margin">They both accepted Commiſſions, and were conſecrated (if at all) by ſuch as had.</note> 
               <hi>Conſecrators of Mat. Parker</hi> were both Intruders and Commiſſion-Officers, and ſuch as the Queen would not make uſe of in her Coronation, tho' ſhe was hard put to it to get any other. Nor has this <hi>Fundamental Fault</hi> ever been rectified, tho' there was once a fair <hi>Opportunity,</hi> by a true <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> ſome time reſident in the Nation, had the Opportunity been wiſely improved, and the Perſon treated as his real Dignity and great Learning juſtly deſerved. So that you have neither any clear <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from Chriſt, nor <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> with the Catholick Church, nor Integrity of his <hi>Worſhip,</hi> nor Authority or Uſe of his <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> nor Evidence or any Demonſtration of the Preſence or Power of his <hi>Spirit:</hi> And in all theſe the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> ſeem to be equal with you, or in a better and ſafer Condition; and tho'
<note n="‖" place="margin">They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray not the Rights of Chriſt's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; their Separation is from Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks; their Non-obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Laws for Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifiable or excuſable by the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of their Adverſaries. <hi>v. Hammond of Schiſm, c.</hi> 2. §. 5, 7,</note> guilty of Schiſm too, yet more innocently guilty, and more cordial and induſtrious for promoting the Spirit and Power of Religion in the Nation, which may be accepted in Mitigation of the Guilt, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if after notice they proceed cautiouſly, and preſume not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106332:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>their Authority, and ſuch things as are lawful and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in all Chriſtians, as Prayer, and Inſtruction of their Neigbours, if done in due manner. And this I think ſufficient for the preſent to juſtifie to a Man of Learning and Underſtanding in theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, both my refuſal of your Communion, and what I told you I am ready to anſwer for in my <hi>Preface</hi> to the Diſcourſe <hi>Of prayers for the Dead.</hi> And if this be not enough, more I have to ſay.</p>
            <p>Theſe things I was willing to have diſcourſed with your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in private, but, it ſeems, it was not the Will of God that I ſhould, but rather offer them publickly to the Conſideration of all. Nor do I ſee any Inconvenience at all in it: For if I be miſtaken in any thing, I ſhall be glad to be better informed, and as concerned and careful to do right to the Truth, as any one concerned can deſire. But if theſe things be ſo, as I have ſaid, certainly they are not to be neglected; nor can any Man, who has any Senſe of his Duty to God, or any Love to his Country, ſee it in ſuch a Caſe, and be ſilent, or not ſo much as give Notice to all, and eſpecially to ſuch as are obliged to take care, not only of themſelves, but of the reſt alſo. Nor can Your Lordſhip, or any of Your Order, be offended at it, if it be truth: for if ſo, it is in effect but what you your ſelves ought to do, as you will anſwer it to Almighty God. If your Prince and the State be guilty of <hi>Sacrilege,</hi> by Uſurping the Sacred Rights of the Church, you ought to admoniſh them, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade them, to oppoſe and withſtand it, and not to comply with it: for that is to make your ſelves Partakers in the Sin, to betray their Souls, and your own too. If all be guilty of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> you ought to conſider how
<note n="*" place="margin">Bp. <hi>Bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hell</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from the Catholic Church to be Separation from Chriſt, and all his holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and from the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of his Paſſion, and all Hope of Salvation. <hi>Vindic. c</hi> 9 <hi>p.</hi> 126. <hi>v</hi> Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond of Schiſm, <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect</hi> 5.6 7, 8. Stillingfleet of Separation <hi>Par.</hi> 2. <hi>Sect.</hi> 27, 28. Dod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well of Schiſm, <hi>c.</hi> 13, 14 Abſtract, <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 16.</note> great a Sin that is, give Warning, adviſe what is to be done, and not conceal ſo great an Evil, either for your own private Intereſt, or for the ſake of a Party: that is to let them die in their Sin, and their Blood be required of you, over and beſides your own Perſonal Guilt. If the Authority of <hi>Chriſt's Commiſſion</hi> be not duly and ſufficiently conveyed to you, you ought not to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to any ſuch thing, or to act as if it was; <hi>that is,</hi> to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit your Soveraign's Commiſſion, to be Impoſtors, and the greateſt Cheats and Deceivers that can be. And all this is no leſs a Sin than that great Sin of diſowning Chriſt, and his Word, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed or afraid to atteſt it; but rather ſo much greater, by how much the Temptation is leſſer. So that it is a matter which deſerves as great Conſideration as any in the World; and not to be reſolved but upon very great and clear Grounds and Reaſons. And if you your ſelves will not be ſenſible of it, others ought, at leaſt every one for themſelves. And ſo I leave it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106332:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
